# Tom Cantellow

A quantitative human geographer specialising in politics and economics with expertise in data-driven insights.

<u> Website | Linkedin | t.cantellow@bristol.ac.uk</u>

### Core Competencies & Technical Skills

- Quantitative Research & Analysis: Advanced statistical skills with expertise in spatial analysis and static and interactive data visualisation (R, Excel, QGIS, ArcGIS, SQL).
- Project Leadership & Collaboration:
   Effective in both self-directed roles and team-based projects, with strong skills in pragmatic decision-making, creative problem-solving, and delivering complex, multi-phase projects on time
- Communication & Teaching: Experienced educator adept at accessibly communicating complex research to diverse audiences.
- **Policy Evaluation:** Strong background in policy research and developing strategic frameworks.

- Survey Design & Implementation: Expertise in creating, implementing, and analysing surveys, tailored to specific research and policy needs, ensuring insights are actionable and relevant.
- **Document and Web Design:** Proficient in creating visually engaging reports, documents, presentations, images, and websites. Self-taught in various tools and with strong intuition for good visual design.
- **Document and Web Design:** Proficient in creating visually compelling reports, presentations, graphics, and websites with a strong eye for design and layout. Self-taught in various design tools, with an intuitive approach to effective and accessible visual communication.

### **Professional Experience**

#### **Teacher, University of Bristol** September 2020 - Present

• Designed and led lectures and workshops for *Bristol Futures: Understanding Global Problems Using Data* unit, teaching quantitative analysis for interdisciplinary undergraduate groups.

Designed and delivered GIS-based Political Geography workshops to sixth-form students as

part of the Access to Bristol widening participation initiative.

• Conducted seminars and marked assessments across multiple geographic sub-disciplines, including political, economic, urban, and health geographies.

 Offered academic guidance and mentorship to students, providing support on both academic and career development.

#### **Research Associate, University of Bristol**

1. *June* 2024 - *Present* 

Developed a **Net-Zero Vulnerability Index** ranking UK areas by vulnerability to green economic restructuring; contributed to writing <u>public report</u>, academic article, and built interactive <u>website</u> for public and policy engagement.

2. April 2023 - September 2023

<u>Analysed and reported</u> on energy efficiency disparities in Bristol, producing recommendations for rental housing energy efficiency improvements, and accompanying webmap.

#### **Geospatial Analyst, DEMOS (Freelance)**

April 2023 - May 2023

Working with the team at Demos, I produced all maps included in the <u>2023 Good Credit Index</u> <u>Report</u>.

# UKRI Policy Intern, UK Home Office, Central Analysis and Insights Team *June* 2022 – *September* 2022

- Enhanced literature review methodology by creating accessibly, dashboard-driven system for evaluating internal and grey literature sources, improving multi-user review capabilities.
- Led analytical initiatives in data visualisation, spatial analysis, survey design, and written and verbal communications tailored for non-expert audiences.
- Managed tasks, upskilled team members, and provided mentorship to junior interns.
- Consulted on evaluative survey redesign, aligning with customers' specific requirements.

#### Education

PhD, Human Geography, University of Bristol

October 2020 — November 2024. Viva Voce passed on 27th November 2024.

Thesis: The 'New Divides' of Neoliberalism: Analysing Economic and Cultural Dynamics in UK Politics

Applies neoliberalism as an analytical framework to examine how personal finance, house prices, and immigration rates intersect with economic and cultural political values to influence political preferences in the UK. The research analyses large datasets (e.g., Land Registry Price Paid Data) and national surveys (e.g., UK Household Longitudinal Survey, British Election Study) and arealevel data using multilevel modelling and descriptive analysis.

# MSc (Distinction), Applied GIS, University of Sheffield September 2017 — September 2018

Thesis: The A Spatial Examination of Populism and Absenteeism in the UK in the Context of the 2016 EU Referendum

- Awarded Sheffield Postgraduate Scholarship in recognition of academic achievement.
- Awarded Ian Masser Prize for best dissertation utilising spatial and statistical analysis to examine the drivers of populism and spatial variations in voting outcomes in the context of Brexit.

# BA (Hons) (2:1) International Relations, University of Lincoln September 2012 — May 2016

- Undergraduate dissertation comparatively analysed outcomes of drug policies of the UK and Portugal.
- Included an international study year at Ghent University in Belgium as part of EU's Erasmus scheme.

#### Voluntary Experience

Postgraduate Representative and Peer Mentor. University of Bristol, 2022.

Nominated for a Bristol STAR award for contributions to positive and inclusive research culture; supported peers through mentorship, event coordination, data collection and presentation, and representing postgraduate concerns in various committees.

#### Research Funding

2024, Disseminating a net-zero vulnerability index, Economic and Social Research Council Impact Acceleration Account, £2,247, Co-I

2024, Developing a net-zero vulnerability index, Bristol Poverty Institute, £3,370, Co-I

2023, Household energy efficiency and restorative justice: The case of the private rental sector. UoB Just Transformation of Energy Systems Fund, £8,831, Co-I

### **Publications**

- Cantellow, T., Atkins, E. "Devising a net zero resilience index: A note on methods" [Report] *Policy Bristol*. Available at: https://www.bristol.ac.uk/media-library/sites/policybristol/briefings/Devising%20a%20net%20zero%20resilience%20index,%20a%20note%20on%20methods.pdf
- Cantellow, T., Atkins, E., Fox, S., Robinson, C. "A Net Zero Resilience Index for UK regions." *Regional Studies.* (Under Review)
- Atkins, E., Robinson, C., Cantellow, T. "The salt fringe as an energy periphery: Energy efficiency in the private rental sector of seaside towns in England and Wales." *Geo: Geography and Environment* (Under Review)
- Cantellow, T., Atkins, E., Fox, S., Robinson, C. "A new net zero vulnerability index finds that jobs vulnerable to decarbonisation require a regional approach." [Report] *Policy Bristol*. Available at: https://www.bristol.ac.uk/policybristol/policy-briefings/net-zero-decarbonisation-economy/
- Cantellow, T., Atkins, E., "Retrofitting Rentals: Exploring the energy efficiency of resi dential dwellings in Bristol." [Report] *Policy Bristol*. Available at: Retrofitting Rentals: Exploring the energy efficiency of residential dwellings in Bristol. Available at: https://www.bristol.ac.uk/policybristol/policy-engagement-projects/retrofitting-rentals-bristol/